Alright.
Welcome back, and this is the final
lecture of week one, The Hybrids.
Now just kind of as review, you know, one
to bring up again, the, the family of
Equidae.
And that includes horses, donkeys, and
zebras, and so the hybrids
is going to be the, the combination of, of
two of those.
So you can see the general definition of a
hybrid, and you
know, it's important to, to kind of
understand how these come about.
So, if I was going to take say a Shire
horse and breed
it to a thoroughbred both are equus
caballus so that's not a hybrid.
That's a crossbred.
So, that wouldn't be considered what we
call hybrid.
But, if you took that Shire horse and bred
it to a Mammoth Jack
donkey which I would really like to see
the offspring of, of these matings.
So that's Equus caballus and Equus asinus,
then you would get a hybrid.
So that's two species, distinct species
that you're breeding.
Now, creating hybrids within Equids is not
really that easy.
And it's really because a lot of the
Equids have a different total number of
chromosomes.
And so it's worthwhile to just kind of
briefly cover what chromosomes
are and how they come about you know,
forming new organisms.
Now the chromosomes are stored in, in the
nucleus of almost
all cells and that contains all the DNA or
genetic material, you
know and tells it to do its function or
program or
develop into a baby horse and, and so on
and so forth.
Now, during mating half the genetic
material comes from
mom and half the genetic material comes
from dad.
They come together and they combine and
form you know, offspring or the foal.
So, if we took the example of the horse,
the
mom has in her oocyte or her eggs, has 32
chromosomes.
And then dad's cell, the sperm cell that
comes in and fertilizes the egg has 32
chromosomes.
They combine and the horse is going to
have a total of 64 chromosomes per cell.
So, so that's important to remember.
Now again, when these chromosomes come
together, you
have one from mom and one from dad.
And so they're going to come and combine
and match up like this.
And then those are, that's chromosome, say
that's chromosome one.
And then, individual chromosome two from
mom, individual chromosome
two from dad comes together, fuses, that's
chromosome two.
Then chromosome three, and so forth.
You know, through all of the chromosomes
of
the horse to where there's 64 total
chromosomes.
So we can say the horse has 64.
Now when we go through the other Equids,
say donkeys, they have 62.
So you know, and we're going to talk about
mules and hinnies here in a second,
but when you mate a horse and mate
a donkey, the offspring's going to have 63
chromosomes.
Which is a mule or a hinny.
Now, the three different zebra species
actually have different chromosomes.
So, it complicates it a little bit more.
So, the plain zebra has 44, and then the
mountain zebra has 32.
And then the Grevy's zebra has 46.
So you can see the Mountain zebra has
the lowest of any Equid with only 32
chromosomes.
So half of what a horse has.
So when you're mating these two species
with the horse oocyte
with 32 chromosomes and the Mountain zebra
who has 32 total chromosomes.
So when I say that remember half comes
from mom half comes from dad.
So their egg and sperm have half that
number.
So 32 so it's 16.
So the mountain zebra sperm cell only has
16 chromosomes.
It's going to come together, line up with
that horse oocyte, line up 16 chromosomes,
and then that actually leaves 16
individual
chromosomes from the horse with no, no
pairing.
So, those genes that are there, that are,
that, that those genetics are, are in
essence, lost.
So, that's why a lot of these hybrids
fail, because you're
not getting proper you know, combination
of the genes to produce offspring.
Now, we're going to talk about the, the
first hybrid is
the horse and donkey hybrid, and it
results in two types.
So if you mate a female horse to a male
donkey or
a jack, so a mare to a jack, you get a
mule.
And what's interesting is this, this is
pretty successful.
So, they get a 90% ferti, fertility rate,
you know, really good fertilization rate
and reproductive rate.
And that's probably why we see so many
mules
in the world today, over 10 million, is
because
you made them and, just, just like any
other
horses, or donkeys, you know they, they
have good rates.
Now when you do the reverse, and so you do
a jenny, or a
female donkey to a stallion, or a male
horse, we don't see the same results.
And this is called a hinny.
And they actually have fertilization rates
or fertility rates less than 15%.
So, that's why they're a lot more rare.
So, you know, in science, at, as
scientists,
we have not really found the reason why.
You know, we've looked in the literature,
and there's really no
reason why this doesn't work as well as
the reverse, making mules.
Now, it's also remember, important to
remember that
their offspring are going to have 63 total
chromosomes.
So you got 64 from the horse, 62, 62 from
the donkey.
You know, you bring those together, you're
going to get 63 and they're going to be
sterile.
So that's why you don't see mules
breeding, because they're sterile.
Now horse and zebra hybrids have, have
been successful, and they have
actually been successful across all three
zebra species, which is really
interesting.
So, it is possible, but, you know, their
fertility rates aren't, aren't as great,
as you'll see.
These are actually called Zorses or
Zebroids.
Now Zebroids can mean you know, as we'll
see in a second, the horse and donkey
hybrids.
But I like to just think of Zorses.
I think its a, its a cool name and, and
every time I see
pictures of these I'm always amazed you
know, that, that they were successful
doing that.
And again their fertility is greatly
reduced because the
mixing of those chromosomes doesn't always
result in, in offspring.
Now, donkey and zebra hybrids, those are
possible too.
And again, they're known as Zebroids, but,
or, you can call
them Zonkeys which again, is a kind of a
cool name.
So, you know call them a Zonkey.
And their fertility again is greatly
reduced.
The mixing of those chromosomes doesn't
always work right, so you know, it, it's
kind of a, somewhat more rare occurrence
than breeding two of the same species.
So, this brings us to the end of week one.
And, you know, thank you for, for taking
the time to watch all the lectures.
Just a quick reminder, take quiz one and
for next week, we're going to start
jumping into physiology.
We're going to start talking a little bit
about coat
colors, some more, some more terminology,
and then jump into
hoof care and then kind of develop you
know, a hoof
care plan, and I look forward to seeing
you then.