So welcome back, and in this lecture we're
going to talk about breeds of horses and
you may notice something
a little different and, and
that's the facial hair right.
So, what this is,
is, is a re recording of a lecture
that I gave the last time we ran it.
And we decided, you know, there's
a couple of errors in there, and, and
one of the most glaring, and I still
love telling this story is, in there,
when Trish and I start talking about
ponies, I have in there, Icelandic Pony.
And, something I learned
from doing this class.
Is you never call
an Icelandic horse a pony.
Because they will take offense and they'll
let you know and, and actually we had a,
a really good time on the message
boards laughing about that.
So, you know, we, we decided to re-record
the lecture so this is actually almost
a year later from all the other lectures
and so overtime I grew a beard and,
you know, you let me know on the message
boards if you like it or not.
But hopefully it's not too distracting for
you,
and you can still, enjoy this material.
So, in this lecture, we're, we're,
we're really focusing on horse breeds, and
you can read the definition there.
It's important to remember, to,
to qualify for a breed, you know,
this is a, a, a strain of animals that you
can, you know, their genetics are uniform,
and they pass on from
generation to generation.
Now horses, obviously, you know, thousands
of years ago when they evolved and
were domesticated, you know,
they were used for primarily riding.
And then they needed horses to say, pull
a cart, or, as in our agriculture, in our
own history, got more advanced, you know,
we needed a horse to, to plow a field.
Or some of the donkeys that, you know,
were, were used as pack animals.
So back then and, and
it's even going on today.
People started to, to breen,
breed certain strains of horses and
they developed these horse breeds.
So that's why we have so many today.
Now you can see, you know,
this is a group that is very
distinguishable from each other and
these are characteristics that carry on
from generation to
generation to generation.
So with breeds comes breed registries.
And there's many, many breed registries
throughout the United States,
throughout the world.
That are specific to that breed of horse.
Now, breed registries serve a very,
very important purpose.
They, they also ensure that the breed
stays true to its genetics.
And they keep pedigrees and, and
records of all these animals.
So, a lot of times,
many of these horse breeds and
breed registries, help, you know,
enhance the value of an animal.
And help track, you know, the lineages of,
of your animals and also performance.
So, things like performance records,
stuff like that.
Now, sometimes you'll hear this term grade
horse, and what that means is you have a,
an animal that's kind of mixed
parentage or mixed breeding, so
they can't really be registered with,
say, the quarter horse association,
because it may have some quarter horse,
and it may have some standard bred and
maybe, you know, some morgan in it.
And it, and
it's a mixture of these breeds.
So it's not true to, to one single breed.
And they're called grade horses.
Now, generally grade horses aren't always
worth as much as a registered horse.
That's not always true.
But, but, you know, often times not it is.
Now there's over 175, probably over
180 breeds throughout the world.
There, there's more being
developed all the time.
And there's actually some horse
breeds that, you know, are very rare.
And there are some folks throughout
the world that are fighting to
try to save these breeds.
I know there's a,
there's a couple in Europe.
But you can look at this
website from Oklahoma State.
Probably has the best comprehensive list
of horse breeds that I have found and
you can go through there and you can see
how many different breeds there are,
where they're from and
kind of their history a little bit,
so it's kind of a cool website.
We obviously are not going to have time
to cover all 175, so I'm just going to
highlight some for you and
kind of talk to you about the differences.
Now breeds are generally broken down
into four classification body types.
And they go from Light Horse to
Warmbloods, Heavy Horse, and Ponys.
Now your light horses and
your Warmbloods, very similar body types.
Some people consider Light Horses and
Warmbloods the same thing.
Other people don't.
So just to help you, in this lecture,
I, I divided them out.
But our light horses tend to be our
horses that we consider hot blooded.
Or you know they, they have Thoroughbred,
Arabian, that's where
they originated from.
You know Arabians and Thoroughbreds are
really the, the true hot blooded horses.
Now when I say hot blood what I mean is,
it's not the actual temperature that of
the blood running through their veins.
It's actually their disposition.
So somebody says,
oh that horse is a little bit hot blooded,
meaning they're a little bit,
you know, uptight, you know, a little bit,
you know, high strung type of animal.
And so that's where that,
that hot blooded came from.
Now the sport horse breeds
are generally considered warm bloods,
not quite as, say, flighty as a hot blood.
But not quite as domesticated or, or
docile, let's say, as our heavy horses,
our, our cold blood.
Cold blood again has nothing
to do with temperature.
It actually has to do
with their temperament.
And, and the draft horses,
if you've ever been around them,
are just fantastic animals.
They are just.
They're big puppy dogs.
They, they are really
wonderful to work with.
As big as they are,
I just, the gentle giants.
Wonderful horses.
And, and
that's why we consider them cold blooded.
Because they're, they're kind of docile.
And then I, you know,
I call them ankle biters.
The ponies.
They're, they're also wonderful, too.
So we'll kind of go through give you
some different examples of breeds.
That fit into those categories.
Okay before we jump into, you know, giving
you some examples of the different breeds,
I, I really want to
discuss with you first on,
on what a hand means in
the equine industry.
A lot of times you'll hear this and
they'll say, oh, that horse stands,
you know, 15 hands tall, or
that horse is 16 two hands.
So what does that really mean?
Well, a hand is actually a measurement
of four inches or over 10 centimeters.
So, going up from the base
of the ground to the top
of the withers is how we
measure a horse's height.
And then if say, a horse is 15 hands,
so let me give you an example.
15.
And I multiply that by 4 inches.
That would equal 60 inches tall.
Okay.
So 15 times 4 is 60 inches tall.
Or you can convert that into centimeters.
Now if I said a horse,
let's say he was 15, 2.
Okay, or you'll hear 15 1, 15 2, or 15 3.
We will not say 15 4 because 15
4 would just mean it's 16 hands.
So for each 0.1, 0.2 or 0.3,
that's actually how many inches we,
we add.
So, with 60 we're just
going to add 2 inches.
And that horse, that's 15 2,
would stand 62 inches tall.
So, you know, something you're, you, you
hear quite a bit in the the horse industry
no need to erase it, just leave it there,
is, is hands, so in this lecture,
you know, we'll talk about hands.
And as you can see here in
the light horse breeds.
Here we talk about horses that
generally stand 14 two up to 16 hands.
Now anything under 14 two
is considered a pony.
So the light horses is above that.
And 16 hands is an average,
I mean I've seen, you know.
Quarter horses way above 16 hands,
so that's just a general rule.
And you can see the weight you know
around a thousand pounds on average,
about 1100 pounds on average or
you know 500 kilograms.
And these horses are primarily used for
riding, so the light horse breeds.
But you do find them actually pulling
carts, especially you know a hundred
years ago, before automobiles
became a real big thing.
Or you know, doing some farm work.
Some of these light horses can definitely
do farm work, pull plows and, and
they still are used throughout the world
in some places, you know, for farm work.
You know, and especially in the United
States we still use quarter horses and
others for a lot of our ranching
work that, that folks do.
Now to start with, you know,
you have to start with the Arabian and
the light horse breeds.
This is really the foundational breed for,
for, many, many other breeds, that
you're going to see here in this lecture
and, and others that we won't talk about.
But the Arabian, you know,
really is one that, that we can point to,
has, has a lot of influence
in a lot of modern breeds.
So, you know obviously you
have to talk about them.
And anybody that's
worked around Arabian's,
I mean, beautiful, beautiful animals.
Very high spirited.
Fun to be around.
You know, my students and other people
that I have talked to that have been
around Arabian's, and
I've worked with a few Arabian's.
Just love these animals.
They're just, they're just
wonderful animals to work with.
You can see they're, they're really,
you know, got some neat characteristics.
We, we talk about this dished face
that they have and, you know,
kind of an angular head.
You can see the arched neck,
broad chest, stuff like that.
Just a wonder, wonderful animal and
you can see why people love them and, and
they're still populous
throughout the world, really.
As a favorite horse.
Now going on, you know,
the Arabian's a foundational breed for
the thoroughbred.
And technically, you know, if you if
you really look at a foundational
breed you can always probably go back
to the Arabian but the thoroughbreds,
you know, considered a foundational
breed for many other types of horses and
one we'll talk about next
is the quarter horse.
You know where these thoroughbreds once
they bred true, they form their own breed.
They then form the nucleus of other
breeds, one like is the standard bred too,
you can see a lot of similarities
between thoroughbreds and
standard breds.
So typically, you know, your thoroughbreds
are going to stand taller than 16 hands.
You can definitely see
the Arabian influence in them.
And these are horses that were bred,
you know,
in England to really be endurance horses.
These are horses that can run far,
farther than most others.
And so, you know, in,
in thoroughbred racing,
which is a very popular sport
throughout the world, you know,
primarily it is thoroughbreds
that you see on the racetrack.
These are horses that can run, you know,
up to a mile and a half in a race.
And really can,
can endure that distance pretty well.
Now the quarter horse,
or the American quarter
horse is the most populous breed in
the United States, over 4 million of them.
And really was, was bred, you know, the,
these, these small towns, you know,
in the United States,
they wanted a horse that.
You know unlike a thoroughbred
that can run forever,
they wanted a horse that can maybe, you
know, sprint down the street in a race.
So they started to develop this sprinters
type horse or this quarter horse,
quarter mile horse, that could,
that could sprint really quickly.
So in the United States one of our,
our racing venues as American quarter
horses and, you know, if you ever do go.
Don't expect them to run
a mile like a thoroughbred.
They actually run, you know,
a much shorter distances because
they're known for their sprinter speed.
These horses also have what we call a cow
sense, so, you know, in the old west,
here in the United States,
you always think of the cowboy on
the back of a quarter horse, you know,
riding around, you know, sorting cows.
And, and doing other things, and these
animals are very smart, and able to pick
cows out of a herd and stuff like that,
and I will say, I, Iove quarter horses.
They're some of my favorite breed to work
with, they're very gentle, you know, and
you can read some of the other
characteristics of them.
So, they're really wonderful,
wonderful animals to own, and, to ride.
Now you can see some of
the other light horse breeds.
And, and the two that I really want,
that stand out that I wanted to highlight,
is a saddlebred, and a standardbred.
And sometimes people get
confused between the two.
Because the, you know,
the names sound do familiar.
Now when you think of a saddlebred,
always think of saddle,
riding and to you that should
say this is a gated horse,
this is a horse that has flashy gates that
goes to shows, as you can see in that
top image, where that,
that gentleman's riding a saddle bred.
Now a standardbred is the type
of animal that was actually,
that's used in harness racing.
And they're, they're called
Standardbreds because it used to be
that you had to trot a mile in
two minutes and 30 seconds to,
to meet the standards to be able to
register with that breed registry.
Now that doesn't hold true any more today,
but in their history
that's where it came from.
Now you can see some of
the other light horse breeds.
I three Palomino in there because you
wouldn't think of Palomino as its own
breed but there is a, a Palomino breed
registry here in the United States that's
strictly just based on their color,
much kind of like the Paint Horse,
even though they still have to be,
you know, a light horse body type.
So, you know, just be aware of that.
Now to talk about, you know, probably
some of our audiences favorite horses and
the warm bloods and
the sport horse bloodlines.
Wonderful horses to watch compete.
I mean, just beautiful animals.
Very, very similar to
a light horse body type.
You can see the, the weight and
the, the height very,
very similar maybe a little bit taller.
Than some of our light horses and just
to highlight a couple of these breeds.
Hanoverian originated in Germany,
these are types of horses that you
generally if you watch the Olympics and,
and equestrian events these
are the type of horses that you see.
Again one of the oldest warm bloods, very,
very beautiful animal, the trakehner,
again another one that
originated in Germany.
These are the horses you
usually see in dressage.
Doesn't mean, you know all
dressage horses are trakehners,
I've actually seen Frisians and,
and other, you know,
thoroughbreds, quarterhorses,
all do dressage.
But, you know, some of your, your
high-end dressage animals are trakehners.
And then you can see some
of the other warm bloods.
And you know just in their names
Oldenburg, Bavarian Warmblood.
You can, you can tell these are animals
that, that originated in Europe.
Doesn't mean all the warm bloods
originated in Europe but, but
the vast majority of them have.
And just wonderful animals you
know beautiful sport horses.
Now the cold blooded, the drafts.
And I've already kind of talked about,
you know, the puppy dogs.
These are our big horses.
Our, our, our huge ones that you know,
really were developed for farm work.
People do ride them.
You can ride them.
But again, they, they were meant to,
to pull plows and, and carts and, and, and
heavy stuff like that.
So that's why they were built so heavy.
And just wonderful dispositions,
just wonderful animals.
Now, let's talk about different breeds.
The first one that I'd like
to share is the Shire.
So this is really recognized as
the largest horse breed in the world.
From England.
And then you see this thing
called feathering.
So you, it's typical to see in,
in some of our draft breeds.
You can see this long hair,
you know under the hocks and
the knees and that's called feathering.
So you can see that with our draft horses,
and again you know these these were
horses that originate really from northern
Europe, so in that colder climate.
You know, probably evolved with those, you
know, they were bred to, to have some of
that protection around their lower limbs
to protect it from frostbite and stuff.
Now another very popular one that you see
is the Belgian, and it's from Belgium.
So really kind of known for its sorrel.
You know coat color,
that flaxen tay, tail and
mane, again has some feathering
around those, those lower legs.
I've actually worked with a couple of
Belgian horses who were wonderful,
wonderful animals.
The Percheron I included here because,
my goodness, if you want to see a horse
with a lot of muscle and a huge neck,.
Go look at a Percheron I mean that neck
is enormous and you could imagine,
you know, bred these animals to have that
huge neck so they can hold, you know,
that collar when they,
when they pulled these heavy loads.
The Percheron I saw it was like oh my
goodness it, it really kind of, you know,
just enormous, enormous animal.
Usually grey to black in color and then.
You know, they really don't have
feathering on the, on their legs, you,
you know, maybe a little bit but,
but really not known for that.
And then you can see some other,
the other draft horses.
And here in the United States
the Clydesdale is pretty well-recognized.
Friesian's kind of considered
a light-draft horse.
So, there, there are others throughout
the world, that you can look up.
And then finally the ankle biters.
The fun horses, they, they're great
you know, just funny to watch and
fun to work with and children tend to,
to ride them so it's a really great.
Again like I said anything under 14,
2 is considered a pony.
And just to highlight a couple breeds.
First one, Shetland.
Pretty popular breed.
You know, it's from the, you know,
Shetland Islands around the Arctic Circle.
This one.
Maximum height is 11 2.
So, you know, relatively short.
The Welsh pony is generally
considered good for kids.
But I've seen some people say,
you know, it's like any horse.
It, you know.
They all have different personalities.
So, you know,
there's, I'm sure there's some Welsh
ponies out there that aren't very nice.
But generally, these are,
these have good dispositions.
You know, again, you can see the,
the maximum height, 13 2.
And, that picture's pretty wonderful to,
to, to see.
Jumping, and then the other pony
breeds you can see, you know.
Here in, here in the America's we have
this really, fun, paint, you know,
horse type breed or, or painted body
coat and that's Pony of the Americas and
really, you see these and you think
about the old west and, you know,
American Indians riding horses, you tend
you think of paint horses or paint ponies.
You know, so when I see those Pony,
Pony of the Americas you know,
my imagination runs with that.
The minis, the really really tiny ones.
They, hilarious, I think they're great.
Icelandic horse, it's not a pony.
I just put it there so,
to, to make that clear.
It, it, it is shorter, but it's a horse.
And then the Tibetan pony and then,
obviously there's many others.
So, in the next lecture we're going to
kind of jump into some of the different
breeds of donkeys and asses.
You know, there's many many
of them throughout the world.
So I look forward to seeing you then.
Okay, and
then just one more thing to these credits,
these are photo credits,
these aren't the references that I use.
So, you can go online, on the message
board to see all the different references
that I've used to reference some
of these breeds and then also,
the other materials of the course.