Welcome to the thousands of students from
over
130 different countries that are
registered for this class.
It makes me so excited to be able to
present
this information to so many people from
around the world.
I'm Dr. Chris Mortensen, and this is the
welcome video
to the, the welcome video to the horse
course and.
Here I am standing in the Florida museum
of Natural History,
here on the UF campus and it's just an
amazing place.
That and, and we're so fortunate to be
able to have this on campus.
And I thought, what a perfect setting for
the first week of the course.
Especially as we talk about the history
and evolution
of horses and donkeys and zebras and the
other equids.
Behind me is a if you don't recognize it,
that's a Columbian mammoth.
And, and it was found in North America and
they went extinct about 10,000 years ago.
And that's about when horses were ejected
from
North America as you'll find out this
week.
So the purpose really of this video is to
kind of talk
about the course, the syllabus kind of go
over some of the objectives.
You'll know each week we, you're going to
notice
there's about 60 to 90 minutes worth of
video.
Some of the videos go longer than 15
minutes, and, and
generally those are, are, lectures that
are really, really important information.
Not to say not all of it is, but that's
tend to, that's why they tended to go
a little bit longer, and I chose not to
reshoot them because you know, that's
very, very important information.
So watch those videos at your leisure, and
then if you're, you're interested in
earning a statement of accomplishment or a
statement of accomplishment with
distinction, you will be
asked to, to take each weekly quiz, which
is only ten, it's ten points,
ten questions, multiple choice, so not, I,
not purposely built to be very, very
rigorous.
And then beginning next week, we're going
to ask you to start
turning in weekly assignments and there's
four weekly assignments and the goal of
you know, creating those assignments is
for you to apply the information
that's presented to you in the, in the
lectures to an actual animal.
So either one you own or a hypothetical
animal.
But the idea is to get you thinking about
the management and the
information presented to you and applying
that to, to horse or donkey care.
So also we're going to ask that you
evaluate three of
your peers if you do turn in your, your
weekly assignment.
And you have to really think about it
with,
with thousands and thousands of students
from around the world.
That's the only feasible way we can grade
or evaluate
your work is, is through peer eval, so, I
know
through some other Coursera courses is not
the most popular
option, but really that's the only way we
can do it.
But I'll be, you know, obviously
throughout the course, I'll be monitoring
that and, and, and making sure people are
fair to each other.
So, in addition to you know, quizzes and
weekly assignments.
We also, we are also going to provide
weekly
gaming activities to help prepare you for
the quizzes.
I’ve gone in and, and created some, some
online games and
some app games that you can actually do on
your own.
That’s going to reinforce the material.
They should be fun, you know some of them
are like battleship or jeopardy or.
Some you know, Who Wants to be a
Millionaire type
games that you have to answer questions
relating to the course.
So those will be provided to you, you
know, to, to, to practice and to have
fun with, and then also I highly, highly
encourage you to participate in the
discussion boards.
You know, get to know your other students
I mean we have people from all over the
world so you know, obviously people down
in Australia
or in Asia or in Africa or South America.
You know, we all manage horses a little
bit
differently or donkeys a little bit
differently, so share
your experiences you know, what works for
you, and
all I ask is that you're respectful for
everybody's opinions.
You know, be, be respectful to each other
on the discussion boards.
Now, I'm going to monitor the class,
throughout the next six weeks,
and I'll be checking in with you with a
video, you
know, each week, you know, kind of
addressing some of the
hot button issues that, that people
brought up in the discussion boards.
And, kind of introduce you to that week's
material.
So, so I really look forward to this
class, I'm so
excited to, to get going and I'll, I'll
see you next week.