All right, welcome back and in this
lecture
we are going to kind of explore how horses
have
made such as impact on us and, and in
this slide it's one of my favorite cave
drawings.
You know, obviously cause I have such a
passion for horses and
this is from the Chauvet Cave in France,
and if you've never seen
it I, you know, you can go online and they
have a really
neat really neat section on all the, the
cave artwork that they've found.
And you know, it dates back thousands and
thousands of years.
So you know, horses, obviously have played
a huge role in my promo video.
And I'll say it again and again and again.
Horses are man's true best friend.
I love dogs.
Dogs are awesome, you know?
There's nothing like a, a dog wet kiss,
right?
But horses have been with us every step of
the way
as we have evolved and explored this
planet and as we've
grown horses have been critical in each
stage of you know,
each major stage of our development in the
last few thousand years.
Now early on horses were hunted for food
so you know, it
was just another animal that early man was
hunting these these animals.
And it's important to remember that horse
meat is
still eaten, you know, many parts of the
world today.
So, you know, in, in Mexico, Japan,
Europe, other countries.
You know, it, it is a part of their diet,
and we, we have to
respect that, you know, even though here
in
the United States we, we don't eat horses.
Now this picture, you may, why is this
important?
And, I just kind of threw it up there to
show you, you know, science and the cool
thing about science.
But also, you know, how we've been able
through
cha, DNA evidence, been able to trace the
migratory
route of humans, and as you can see we
all go back to common ancestors in Eastern
Africa.
And men and women have migrated into
Europe, migrated across Asia, came
down into the Americas to where the South
American Indians are actually the most
divergent through genetics, from our most
common ancestor.
And I put this up here because this is how
we're really unlocking
a lot of mysteries in a lot of species
through DNA evidence and
people are actually looking at this now,
currently in horses, to kind of
figure out, you know, where these
horses were domesticated because nobody
really knows.
We don't have firm, firm evidence, but
maybe through some DNA, you know DNA
testing, and we can start developing a
more clearer picture of where this
happened.
So you know, I'm just going to cover three
main areas where people
think horses might have first, you know,
been domesticated over 6000 years ago.
And the first one is in modern day
Ukraine.
There is some evidence that possibly
horses
were first roped and you know somebody
jumped
on the back of them and thought wow this
is fun or this is really great.
Let's do this some more.
So that's one area that people think it
might be and then there are some
evidence that it might have been in China
or Mongolia around the same time period.
You know, possibly this is where horses
were
and then this paper from, from the Levine
that
came out in the, the Equine Vet Journal,
it
proposes the best evidence is actually in
Northern Kazakhstan.
You know, looking at some of the old bones
of
the horses that they found, looking at the
male female ratios.
You know, he was saying in his article
that it was a one to one ratio.
Where in some of these other pastoral
societies, you know, when
they were hunting horses, you know, you
would find, you know, mainly
younger horses or more females and less
males because that's how
horses naturally are, one male to a few
females and their band.
So it was an interesting paper, and, and,
and really
some compelling evidence that this is
where horses were first domesticated.
But, the take-home message is it was
somewhere in this Eurasia area, on the
plains of Asia and Eastern Europe, where
horses were first thought to be
domesticated.
Now, why should we domesticate these
animals?
And the obvious answer is it's fun, but
you can jump on the back of them.
You can go a lot faster than we can run.
You can go further.
And, you know, early on this probably
gave, you know, these early hunters a
huge advantage, you know, being able to
run down prey and, and get them.
And then here's an earlier, you know,
another cave drawing, you know, over
5,000 years ago showing, you know, a man
on the back of a horse.
And as, you know, we, we get more
developed you
know, there's more evidence of horses
being used in different ways.
You know, pulling chariots, starting to
see them
in agriculture, yet they were, they were
still
being raised in many parts of the world as
meat, but also, you know, Beast of Burden.
You know, pulling carts, pulling chariots,
stuff like that.
And they really make a, a huge impact
during the Bronze
Age, so were looking at you know, 3000 to
1000 BCE.
Ane you know, again talking about
travelling distances,
better agriculture but also you know,
increasing trade.
All of this resulting in better nutrition,
you know, more advance society, larger
families,
so again horses are allowing us to have
more people as advance a lot quicker.
So what other species on earth has done
that and there isn't,
horses are it, they are, they are the most
important in our development.
And then again to see, you know, how early
man felt
about these animals, we find that all, all
in their artwork.
This is White Horse Hill in England.
The White Horse of Uffington.
And you can see that it's clearly a
picture, and
it, it's, you know, this chalked outline
of a horse.
Now, just a couple other interesting
tidbits, the first
evidence of use of saddles was the
Assyrian calvalry.
And here you can see in this picture, you
know, showing,
showing that in, you know a soft pad or
blanket type.
Doesn't have stirrups, so, you know, get
incredible horsemen back
then and women, that they could ride these
animals almost bareback.
You know, now they started using blankets,
soft pads, then the wooden
saddles started to be developed, the
framed saddles that we see today.
And then the first evidence of stirrups
actually dates to India.
And it actually goes to these loop rope
stirrups that they would put their toes
in.
So that's, you know, those were the early
stirrups.
And then the metal stirrups started
developing later.
And I think China and then parts of
Europe really started to flourish with the
stirrups.
Now, the horse for thousands of years was,
you
know, critical to our own development, our
daily lives.
Everybody pretty much had some sort of
equid, whether it was
a donkey or a horse or mule or some other
hybrid.
And, you use that to transport, you know,
get around, go to the neighbor's house.
Do the things that you did in your daily
life.
That all changed in the 20th century and
really
the automobile was the major thing that
changed it.
And it you know, I use the United States
as kind of
a, you know, microcosm of what was
probably going on globally, too.
And the, the horse population was about 26
million in 1915.
And then after World War I, with the
Calvary
being really ineffective, and automobiles,
you know, making more and
more of a presence known, horses really
started to
in popularity declined toward the 1960,
you know by 1960.
There was maybe 3 million left in the
United States.
So, it's a huge, huge decrease.
Now we know after 1960, we start to see
this horse population
increase in the United States, to where we
have over 10 million today.
And I like to say people rediscovered the
horse.
You know?
They, they, they found these animals.
Fell back in love with them.
Yeah, we have a car.
Yeah, we have a motorcycle or a bicycle or
whatever.
But it's not the same as riding a horse.
There's just something about it, you know?
Being out-, outdoors, riding the back of
an animal.
And that's what a lot of people have
rediscovered.
And so we've seen this in the United
States, really take off.
And in other parts of the world, I mean,
South
America, huge hotbed of horse activity in,
in Asia and Europe.
So you know, we're not alone here in the
United States.
A lot of people have, have rediscovered
their passions for these animals.
And so we're really seeing it, it pick up
the pace.
So in our next lecture, we're going
kind of jump
in and talk about different breeds, you
know, throughout the
world, there's over 140 breeds of, you
know, horses, and,
and then we'll jump into breeds of donkeys
and whatnot.
But, you know, we're not going to be able
to cover all of them.
So, we're going to take some snapshots
here and there and kind of cover
some of the big breeds in the world, and
you know, go from there.