All right.
Well, welcome to our first lecture, the
World's Equids.
Now you may ask yourself, what's an equid.
And it, it's kind of the term for these
animals that fall under this taxonomic
family known as Equidae.
So you know, the, the, the first one that
falls into Equidae is, is the horse.
Which, you know?
Obviously, this course is about.
And the two scientific terms for the horse
is Equus caballus and Equus ferus.
Now Equus caballus is for the domestic
type horse.
And then Equus ferus is for the wild
type horse, which today is, is the
Przewalski horse.
That's, that's the only one that, that,
that's left of the wild type.
Even though we have you know, feral horses
from Equus caballus that,
that have been released in the wild, and,
and are now feral.
They're still Equus caballus.
Now the next classification of an equid is
a donkey
or an ass, as known throughout many parts
of the world.
And their scientific name is Equus asinus.
And then the final member of this family
is the zebra.
So, you know, there's many subspecies of
Equus that are
zebras that we're going to talk about
later in this lecture.
So, I couldn't really fit them all on this
line here.
But, there's one more that we, we can't
forget about.
So, we have the horses, the donkeys and
the zebras, but you can also consider
these hybrids.
Which, really is the most common is the
mule.
As an equid.
So they, they are equids they're just a
cross
species of you know, Equus caballus and
Equus asinus,
or there's actually zhorses and zonkeys
which in the
lecture later this week that you'll lean
more about.
Now the next thing we want to look at
is the global population and the best
information
I could find is this report from the
Food and Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations.
And they update, you know, livestock
species, you
know, throughout the world, through
surveys or estimations.
And their last estimate from 2011 is,
there's
58,million horses on earth, which is
pretty amazing.
And then if we look at donkeys, or
asses, there's another 43 million equids
out there.
So again, you know, you have 58 million
horses, 43 million donkeys.
And then, this was really surprising to
me.
I didn't realize how many mules we
actually have on Earth, around the world.
And there's over 10 million mules, which
is, which is really cool.
So, overall we're looking at a 111 million
equids, you know,
donkeys, horses and mules around, you
know, many continents and [UNKNOWN].
But the only one whether it's in the horse
because they probably couldn't survive
down there very well.
But you know what's really exciting about
that is, you know, with all of
these, these animals, is there's all those
owners, that are enthusiastic about owning
them.
We actually need them.
In their daily lives to, to run their
business or to get to work or to do
the things that man has been doing with
horses for and donkeys and mules for 6,000
years.
So, pretty exciting data there.
Now if we look at breaking it down by
country, I just listed the top seven.
And the United States came in ranked
number one with over 10 million horses,
which
wasn't too surprising to me because, you
know,
the horse hot bed here in the States.
But you go down this list you know China
has 6.7 million, still huge population of
horses there.
Mexico 6.3 million, breaking it down and
the one country that really
surprised me was Ethiopia with over 2
million head of horses in it.
I was really surprised that they had that
many more than Russia.
And then if you go look at the donkeys
or the asses, Ethiopia's number one with
6.5 million.
You know then again breaking it down, you
know, China, Pakistan, Egypt.
I was fortunate enough to, to be in Egypt
a few years ago and I,
I saw plenty of donkeys still pulling
carts
you know, work in the fields with
agriculture.
You know big part of their life there
in Egypt, beautiful animals, you know
Mexico and then
a couple of other countries in Africa,
Niger and
Nigeria huge populations of donkeys that
are still working.
For their owners today.
And then when you break down this
population of mules, Mexico came in
number one with 3.2 million, and then
China there, Brazil, Morocco, there's
Ethiopia again.
So, Ethiopia has a huge equid population.
Peru and Argentina.
Now we can't forget the other, you know,
the, the wild type animals.
Now Equus ferus, there's a few thousand.
There's Przewalski horses still roaming.
You know, in Mongolia and China they were
re-released, so they're,
they're still out there in some preserves
as we reestablish that population.
So.
Really only the true wild equids are the
zebras and the wild asses.
So if we look first at the plains zebra
you can see their scientific
name Equus quagga and this is what
everybody thinks of when they think of
zebras.
They think back to the Serengeti Plain you
know, in Tanzania, running away from
predators and you know, that's what we
typically think of and there's over 600.
60,000 of these animals.
So they're still doing relatively well in
the wild, but
the other two populations of zebras are,
aren't doing so hot.
The first is the mountain zebra, you
know, Equus zebra, and they're listed as
vulnerable.
There's only about 9,000 of these animals
left
and they're in the southwestern region of,
of Africa.
And what's unique about these animals too
is you can see that dewlap right there.
And that was.
That's important because these animals
are, you know, in hotter parts of Africa.
And that helps them thermoregulate that
extra skin.
So it, it's really cool if you ever see
these at a, at a zoo
or if you're fortunate enough to see them
in the wild, you can see that dewlap.
And it, it, it's pretty unique, to them.
And then the other zebra species is the
Grevy's zebra.
And this is the one that's endangered.
There's, there's about 2000 animals left.
And they range from really central to
southeastern Africa.
And I've done a little bit of work with
these guys.
And you know, really need to be
aware that they are endangered, they're
being overhunted.
You know, they're in competition with,
with livestock in that part of the world.
And, and just kind of a, you know,
something to
be aware of that those animals are, are in
trouble.
And then, you know, we don't want them to
end
up like the quagga here which went extinct
in 1875.
And what's really cool about this one is.
You know, it looks like a half
zebra half donkey, and unfortunately
there's, there's no
live specimens anymore and we, we actually
can't look at these animals in their
beauty.
Now there, there's two major classes of,
of wild donkeys, or wild asses.
And there's the African wild ass and the
Asiatic
wild ass, so our domestic populations came
from these animals.
And what's left of the African wild ass is
really only the Somali wild ass.
And there's maybe 600 animals left in the
world.
And it's really unfortunate.
You can see here the the Somali wild ass.
You know, with that leg striping, these
are beautiful animals.
I've been fortunate enough to do some
research with these guys and I, and
I hope to continue to do research with
them in trying to save this population.
I really hope they don't go extinct in my
lifetime even though that's what
it's looking like as they, they lose their
habitat and, and, and some other problems.
And then.
Next to that is the the Nubian wild ass
that went extinct within probably the last
20 years.
It's certainly extinct in the wild and.
You can see what's unique about this is,
this one had the stripe over the
shoulders.
So when you look at domestic donkeys
today, which we will later in the week.
Looking at breeds of donkeys you can still
see leg stripping and that back
stripe you know, from their original
Nubian wild ass and the Somali wild ass.
Now the Asiatic wild asses, they're,
they're ones
known as you know, the onagers, the
kulans.
These are endangers, so there's maybe
8,000 of these left in the wild.
So again competition with, with humans.
You know also a, a major danger to these
populations is, you know feral
donkeys that get away from their owners
are actually breeding with the wild
population.
So you get a mixing of the genetics and
you no longer have a
true wild, you know Asiatic wild donkey or
a true wild African wild donkey.
So, so anyways, but they, they are out
there and they are part of what's an
equid.
Now, our next lecture is we're going to
start with the evolution of, of the horse
and, to a lesser extent, donkeys and
zebras, where they, they all have common
ancestors.
So, we'll, we'll cover that in much more
detail in the next lecture.