Alright, welcome back.
In this lecture we're going to cover some
different breeds of donkeys found
throughout the world.
Now, just really quickly I want to do a
quick review.
Just so, you kind of remember where
donkeys originated from
and coming from two, you know, regions of
the world.
The Asiatic wild asses, and then the
African wild asses.
And in a lot of the pictures you'll see in
this
lecture, you will be able to, to at least
see some
of the, the similarities in, in the
co-patterns, where you have
that striping along the shoulder, that
came from the Nubian wild ass.
And then the striping on the legs that we
typically see in the Somali wild ass.
So, you'll see that in some of the
pictures of, of the breeds that we have.
Now quickly before we, you know, jump into
the different breeds, we have to cover
some terminology.
Now, in horses, male horses are known as,
as stallions.
In donkeys and in some of the hybrids that
we'll
talk about in,in the next lecture, they're
referred to as jacks.
The females in horses are referred to as
mares where in donkeys they're referred to
as jennies.
Now any stallion or jack that has been
castrated, they're known
as geldings, or specifically in donkeys,
they'll be known as cut-jacks.
And then a foal is a foal, is a foal
so that's, that's, that's similar between
you know, horses and donkeys.
Now the first donkey actually originated
from Ethiopia, and
you can see it's also known as an
Ethiopian donkey.
And you can really see you know, how that
donkey looks so closely resembles
a Nubian wild ass, and a Somali wild ass
with the striping along the shoulder.
And, some of that faded striping along the
legs.
So, you can definitely go, oh yeah, you
can kind of see where that animal came
from.
And then the Anatolia donkey, it
originated in Turkey, so it's, it's you
know, obviously the other side of
the Mediterranean from Ethiopia or further
north.
And I, you know, chose this picture to put
in here to, to make you realize that
donkeys
are still used throughout the world, you
know, for
agriculture and other purposes, so they
are still working animals.
You know, here's some children bringing in
a harvest with their donkey and when I,
when I spent some time in Egypt you know,
I was able to see donkeys pulling
carts and you know, still working and
they're, and they're very important to
those societies
so you know, s, still need to see
them have such an important connection to
humans.
Now the next breed we'll talk about is the
Standard donkey, and this comes really in
three different sizes,
and you can see the the size requirements
or
where they fit in there in inches and in
centimeters.
So, there's the small standard, the
standard, and the
large standard, and these can be all
different coat colors.
You know, which again next week, we'll,
we'll, we'll jump into different coat
colors.
Get you up on that.
Now the next breed is, and I thought it is
a really
cool one to, to put in here is the Mammoth
Jack donkey.
And this is the largest donkey breed in
the world, and they actually have height
restrictions.
You actually have to be taller than, than
those restrictions.
So for jacks it's 14 hands, for jennies
it's 13.2 hands.
So to register with them, you actually
have to
be, your donkey has to actually be taller
than that.
And the largest donkey in the world is
named Romulus and he actually stands 17
hands tall, so you know, as tall as
some largest draft horses Romulus, the
Mammoth Jack.
And then the Mary donkey you could
see what, you know, some other [INAUDIBLE]
whether
the people called the Merv and, and what
not that, and it originated in Iran
and Azerbaijan, so again, you can see some
of that you know, striping from a
Nubian wild ass, and there's probably some
Asiatic
wild ass in there somewhere along the
line.
And then the next one that a lot of people
love seeing are the Miniature donkeys, and
these originated in
the Mediterranean, and the term burro, You
know, really came
from the Americas, and that's what we call
small donkeys.
So these miniature donkeys, or smaller
donkeys of ours,
you know they're, they're kind of known as
burros.
And, for the Miniature donkeys, you know
they can't be taller than
nine hands, so they do have some height
restrictions with, with them.
And then the final breed we'll, we'll talk
about
is the, the p, the Poitou, Poitou donkey
from France.
And what's really cool about these donkeys
is, not only are they tall, so you
can see the long legs on that one, but you
can look at the coat.
I mean, it's really neat looking.
You know, animal has this really long
hair.
Just really looks, looks cool.
So I, I thought it would be fun to
highlight that one.
But again, similar to horses there's many,
many donkey breeds throughout the world.
You know, I didn't want to leave anybody
out but,
you know, don't have time to cover them
all so.
Still great animals to work with.
Now the next lecture, we're going to, you
know, kind of close out the week,
talking about the hybrids, and how do we
come about with these hybrids.
And, and so I look forward to seeing you
then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]