All right, welcome back, and in this
lecture we're going to
kind of finish up on, you know, this hoof
care and,
and, you know, hoof anatomy talk with a
talk on
laminitis, and I felt it was really
important that we
devote a little bit of time, kind of
talking about
laminitis because it is such a terrible
affliction for horses,
donkeys, and other equids Now I start this
lecture off
talking about Barbaro and for many people
that may remember
Barbaro, in 2006 he won the Kentucky Derby
in fantastic fashion and there was a
lot of talk that this was the next Triple
Crown Winner and, and I know
that we, we kind of say that every year
with the, the Kentucky Derby winner, but
Barbaro was just such a phenomenal
athlete, that
people were really starting to, to believe
this.
And, he was going to the Preakness, which
is the second
leg of the Triple Crown, and he was the
heavy favorite, and
he, in the initial stretch run you know,
passing through in
front of the grandstands, he was suddenly
pulled up by his jockey.
The jockey jumps off and you can see
there, these were some pictures that were
taken
immediately, and he had broken his cannon
bone,
his sesamoid bone, bone and the long
pastern bone.
And so he was immediately out of the race
and everybody's attention you know, turned
away from you know, we don't care about
the race we now care about Barbaro.
So, he was carried by an ambulance that
was covered
by the new, all the news channels here in
the United
States, as they went up the highway to New
Bolton Center
up in Pennsylvania which is a, a world
renowned equine hospital.
And he went under, underwent surgery to
repair those,
those broken bones, as you can see in
these X-rays.
That's the, the initial broken right hind
leg, and then, after all the surgery he
went through, which was led by Dr. Dean
Richardson and his surgical team did this.
And I was actually very fortunate to, to
listen to him speak after this incident
happened.
And kind of the phenomenal, you know,
skills
that these veterinarians have in repairing
the leg.
So, Barbaro went through surgery and, and
his right hind leg was, was healing well.
He, he was, he was on the mend and,
and things were looking really, really
good for him, but
then unfortunately, a few months later, he
started to show
signs of, of laminitis in his hind left
leg, and
as you can imagine, you know, he couldn't
rest his
weight on his right legs, so he rest it
all
on his hind weight on his left leg, and
that
had a, a dramatic impact on the hoof
health there.
So he went through another round of
surgeries, and this is a picture after
some of the surgeries, where they, they
went in and tried to, to help
repair some of that damage in that hind
left leg with the laminitis, and
again he seemed to rebound and do really
well, and he was on the mend.
But then unfortunately again, you know,
with not being able to
put weight on those hind legs, all the
weight was on the
front end of, of Barbaro, his, both his
front legs started to
become laminitic, and he started to, to
lose function of those hooves.
And just due to the, the, you know, poor
quality of life that, that he was leading
and, and Dr. Richardson actually, you
know, you
could still hear the, the pain in his
voice.
They euthanized Barbaro in January 2007.
And I, I use this story just to kind of,
you know, capture your
attention and, and to really underline how
important it is to care for a horse's
feet, or a donkey's feet, or, or a mule's
feet, and, you know, how
to take care of them and prevent some of
these things that can cause laminitis.
Now, so now we'll kind of go in to what is
laminitis, and sometimes you'll hear
this referred to as founder, so that's a
common term that, that people use it.
But what happens is, you know, laminitis,
laminae, remember going back
to our hoof anatomy, is you get
inflammation in that laminae, and
so there's an interrupted blood supply,
and you start to get some,
some breakdown of the lamina sheets that's
holding everything together in there.
So we go back to our hoof anatomy, and we
remember
this, this laminar interface where we have
these interlocking fingers and
sheets of laminae that are holding that
outer hoof wall with
that inner hoof, and then you also have
the coffin bone here.
So, all of that, that laminae is holding
that in place.
Well, when you get some of this
inflammation and some breakdown of that
interface,
you start to get some what we, we see
rotation of the coffin bone.
So what's pulling on that coffin bone is,
if you
remember that deep digital flexor tendon
that's running down here, okay.
So when you get disrupted blood supply
here, and this laminar interface starts
to break down, it will start to pull and
rotate that cannon bone.
And I have some more, better pictures of
it, it's going to illustrate this for you.
But that's where we start to see the
breakdown in, in the hoof.
Now, again, this is a very painful
condition for horses, and if you can
imagine, just like our finger bed, finger
bed, our fingernails in, in the bed.
You know, if we ever get tears there, or
even little infections,
you know, it's extremely painful because
of so many nerve endings down there.
So again, like with horses, they also, you
know, have that nerves there that's very
painful.
Now, if we look at the normal anatomy of
the hoof you can see that and you know,
with
almost the coffin bone almost pointing
straight down, but
not quite, it's almost like they're on
their tippy toes.
But, again when we get that breakdown, and
you
can see that, that green arrow that's
showing you that's
where you start to get that, that
breakdown of
the lamina, and it starts to pull that
coffin bone.
Now, looking at these slides, you can see
where that coffin
bone starts to rotate, and then it also
sinks down so
as that tendon just keeps pulling,
pulling, pulling and it breaks
away from the, the hoof, the outer hoof
wall, it can sink.
And then you can see there's different
case, different severity of laminitis
where it can
be a mild form, where you get some
mild rotation, some moderate or very, very
severe.
And these severe cases are the ones that
are,
that are really, you know, you get worried
about.
And here you can see on an X-ray of
a real horse where that bone has rotated
severely.
And then also here in the bottom picture,
you know, a cross
section where you can see those
white arrows are highlighting where
there's inflammation.
And then you actually have instances of
that
coffin bone poking through the bottom of
the hoof.
So again, a very, very serious disease, a
serious condition in horses.
So what can cause this, and what, what can
you
do to manage, to limit your horse from
getting laminitis?
Well, one of the main causes is,
is overeating, or specifically overeating
of grain.
And what this does is, is, is grain's a
very energy dense meal, lots of
carbohydrates that gets
in the gut and, specifically, the hind gut
of
the horse, and we'll talk more about
nutrition next
week, and the bacteria there goes, they go
crazy
because there's so many nutrients and then
they, they
start to die off and and when they die
off they release endotoxins that're
absorbed by the horse.
And then carried down through the blood
stream,
again remember that, that blood supply to
the hoof.
And then that's where you start to get the
breakdown of the lamina interface.
Now, another cause is what we call road
founder, and these are on horses that
are either worked too long or too hard on,
on you know, hard asphalt or concrete.
Now if you go back to the hoof care,
that's where we get
into, we were talking about shoeing, you
know maybe get some of these rubber
shoes, maybe with a little bit of extra
cushion, especially on these horses
that, that have to work on these surfaces
for, for long periods of time.
And then there's a thing called water
founder, and this is,
you know, imagine a horse that's going
through some intense exercise or
riding and then you allow them and they
get really overheated
and then you go allow them to drink lots
of cold water.
You know that's, again, a shock to the
system, and can result in, in founder.
Couple other causes, sometimes we see this
in, in mares
after, you know, giving birth to their
foals, or through parturition.
If they suffer from a uterine infection
after give, after
giving birth, or if they have a retained
placenta, so
a placenta that's been in, you know,
retained for four
hours or more, you know, they're at risk
of laminitis.
And then there's another one is, is called
grass
founder, and this is horses that are
eating lush pasture.
Now next week again, we'll talk, we'll get
more in
to nutrition and feeding strategies, but
it, it's worth mentioning here.
Young pastures, or lush pastures, is
really the young growth, like, you meant,
you know, imagine early spring, lots of
rain, everything, we call it greening up.
You know, the grass is growing.
Well, these, these young grasses and
legumes,
especially when they're really short or
just stuffed
with energy, they have a lot of
carbohydrates, a lot of simple sugars in
there.
And so, if you turn out a horse that's
been eating
hay for a long time, you know, something
that's, that's dry and,
and less energy-dense, and you turn him
out on a lush
pasture, they're getting tons and tons of
energy in their digestive tract.
Again, it's almost going back to
overeating.
So, there's different strategies you, you
can
do to limit which we're going to cover.
You know, which leads me right into
management tips, and
the first thing you can do is, you always
want
to secure and store your feed properly and
we'll touch
upon this maybe, a little bit more next
week, too.
You know, horses are, are, are very
inquisitive,
and the picture on, on the right is
actually from a video of this Friesian
horse
that was getting in out of, letting
themselves out
of his stall, actually it's a pretty funny
video, if you can find it on YouTube, and
actually goes by a stall, says, oh, you're
not my friend, goes down to the next
stall.
And that's, that's the horse unlocking
that stall to let them out.
Well they'll let themselves out.
They'll go to the feed room, and if your
feed's not secure,
they will gorge themselves and eat as much
grain as they can.
So you know, they're, they're, they're
overwhelming their digestive
tract, digestive system, and that can lead
to laminitis.
So you want to make sure all your feed's
properly secured
and stored, so that a horse does not get
out.
Now, you know again nut, we'll talk about
nutrient requirements next week and also
how to add
weight to a horse safely, you know, you do
this in a safe manner rather than
overfeeding them.
And this picture is obviously not a real
horse, if anybody was wondering, but
I just love this picture because you know
everybody always laughs when they see it.
It's, it's, it's something I use to really
illustrate you do not want overfeed your,
your horses.
Now getting back to you know, this lush
forage, you know, some strategies you
may want to employ is you know, what we
call limited turn out time.
So especially a horse that's been you
know, eating lots
of hay you know, dry hay, over, say, over
winter and
you're going to release them out in the
spring or,
or they're stalled a lot or kept in
paddocks a lot.
You know, you have this lush pasture that
you want to put them out on.
You know, day one, you put them out for
20,
30 minutes max and then pull them back,
back in.
And then you increase that time slowly.
And this allows the digestive tract to
adjust to these nutrient-dense grasses.
Other things you can do, you can feed them
hay before you turn them out on pasture.
They do get a thing called gut fill, so
they can fill up their stomachs with hay,
and
then they are not going to graze as much,
or you can get these things that are
called grazing
muzzles, that go over them and they can
nibble
a little bit through there on the longer
stemmed
forage, but these really young grasses,
they have a
really difficult time pulling them up and
getting at them.
So, so there's different strategies you
can use to try to limit that.
And then also, horses need exercise.
I mean, especially if they're kept in
stalls or small paddocks.
They need to get out, they need to run,
they need to
get the fresh air, they need to be able to
be a horse.
It's not just for their mental well being,
but also for their, their physical health.
You know, and hoof health.
So again, if, if you are keeping a horse
stalled, you do not, they need
to get turned out daily for at least an
hour, if not two hours or more.
And then just finally, proper hoof care.
I mean, this is where, you know, the
purpose of, of covering these last
couple lectures is again, to underline how
important it is to care for their feet.
Because if you go back to that first
saying, no hoof,
no horse or no hoof, no donkey or no hoof,
no mule.
You know you need to really take care of
their feet, and manage
them nutritionally to prevent some of
these
you know, terrible disorders that we see.
So, now we're going to turn to some fun,
more exciting than, than laminitis.
It, it's just, I, I think laminitis is
something that we really, really needed to
cover.
But next, we're going to start going
into things like coat colors, identifying
horses.
You know, we'll look at markings, and then
that will wrap
up week two, so
I'll see you then.