Alright.
Welcome to week two of the horse course.
And in the first lecture we're going to
start talking about basic equine
physiology or horse physiology.
And we're going to use the horse, but
again, all this
will apply to the other subspecies,
donkeys, zebras, and what have you.
So the basic anatomy of a horse is very
similar
to other livestock species but there are
some key differences.
And, it's really important to understand
at least their external physiology
and the terms associated with that because
a lot of the terms.
You know, not only are we going to be
referring to them, you know,
throughout this course which we've already
done
the previous week and, and going forward.
But, you know, any time you're involved in
the
horse industry or you own donkeys, you
know, you're
going to need to know these terms because
we, you
know, we call specific parts of their
bodies specific things.
So that's kind of why we, we felt that it
was important
to kind of you know, address this in just
one lecture.
But obviously, you know, you could take
an entire Coursera course talking about
just physiology.
So, you know, we're going to go cover.
What we can this week, you know, and then
going forward in the course.
So, this is just the outlet, outlay,
outlaying
area of the horse and the external
anatomy.
And, and I know it kind of looks a lot at
first, but once you start calling
it and getting used to calling certain
terms,
you know, it, it, it becomes relatively
easy and.
You know, before we jump in kind of look
at specific areas of the
horse I, I did want to bring this up that,
70% of a horse's
weight is in its front end and, you know,
we're going to look at
skeletal anatomy briefly and you'll see,
you know, some of the, the reasons why.
But, you know, not only do you have the
large, you know,
chest, shoulders but the neck and the head
all forward of the horse.
So that's where a lot of weight is.
In these animals.
Now, if we just focus in on, you know,
the front portion of the horse, you know,
you're
going to, starting with the bottom of the
chin, or
what we call the throat latch working it's
way over.
And I did kind of want to highlight the
crest here, and
that's just, is the area running, you
know, all along down the neck.
And sometimes you'll hear people say a
horse is cresty.
Now sometimes that means, you know,
they're arching their neck.
You know, we see this with stallions quite
a lot,
you know, when they're around mares and
kind of showing off.
But also horses that are overweight, you
know, we'll call them cresty in the neck.
And that's just because that's an area
where they deposit a lot of fat.
And starting in week four when we get into
nutrition.
We'll, we'll talk more about body
condition.
So, one area to, to kind of put away so
when we get to nutrition, you can kind of
remember that.
Now, working your way down the back of the
horse, you can see the shoulders and
then of course the withers, you know, we,
we talk about the withers quite a lot.
We've already talked about the withers,
you know, especially when
we talked about hands, you know, measuring
the height of
the horse from the withers to the ground
and then
working your way back, you know, the back
and the loin.
And then, you know, if you just imagine
this
is where a rider would almost sit, and
they're
kind of in between the back and the loin,
you know, and then going down to the tail.
Now looking underneath the horse, you
know, what you
will find is if you look at the canon
area.
Down, on all four legs the, those
structures are all called the same, so,
you know, you have the cannon going down
to the fetlock, the pastern, and the hoof.
So that's similar between all four front
and back legs.
But when you start dividing front versus
back, you do start to see differences.
So in the front you've got the knee, the
forearm, the elbow.
And then in the back, you've got the hock,
the gaskin, and then going up to the
stifle.
Okay, so there are differences.
So it's almost like our, our, our front
arms are in the front half of the horse.
And our legs are in the back half of the
horse.
And that will be important too when we
look at some of the skeletal anatomy.
You'll see some of the familiar terms.
So jumping into that I do want to
say, you know, don't worry about
memorizing certain bones.
It's not going to be on an exam or a quiz
but I do want to address it
just so you kind of see, you know, the
horse
and the skeletal structure and where,
where it is.
Again, 70% of the weight.
So it's not hard to see from this slide.
Looking at the large rib area, the neck,
the, the cranium.
You know, all that weight in the front
half of the horse, you know?
That's where you, you know?
It's easier to see that.
Now, if we start at the top.
You know, just some basic terms of the
cranium and the teeth and, and the neck.
But what's interesting is the horse does
have this kind of S
orientation of the cervical vertebrae and
what's really supporting the neck not only
is the bone structure supporting the neck
but you do have a ligaments
or series of ligaments and then quite a
bit of muscling in there.
So that's really what's helping support
the, the head carriage of the horse.
So, so kind of every time, you know, you
see
a horse skeleton you see that it's kind of
surprising.
Now, if we just looked at the barrel of
the horse of
the, the main body of the horse I mean
obviously they, they
have a large shoulder, large scapula bone
and then you could see
the, the different vertebrae going from
the thoracic down to the tail.
Two areas I did want to highlight is again
similar to external anatomy.
That front portion is, is almost like our
arm.
So that's the humerus bone which is what
called here on,
on us and then they have the femur in the
back leg.
Which is similar to our large leg bone,
our femur.
Now looking at the lower anatomy, skeletal
anatomy again very similar like the
external anatomy from the cannon bone down
all four legs are the same.
So you're looking at, at similar
terminology with the
long pastern, the short pastern, and then
the coffin bone.
From that point upwards, there's
differences
between the front and hind legs.
So, in the front, again, you have the
knee, the carpus.
But, ag, you know, again, in reference to
arm, the
radius and ulna which is actually our
lower arm bones.
So, that's where that is in the horse.
And then in, in the hind end of the horse,
obviously you have the hocks.
But going up, you know, we have that
femur.
But then you have the tibia and fibia
which again, similar to, to our lower leg.
There's two bones there.
So, so some things just to, to kind of
remember with skeletal anatomy.
Now, muscle anatomy.
You're probably thanking me that we will
not go over this quite a bit.
It's pretty in depth, it actually gives
you a really great appreciation for, you
know, your veterinarians and other medical
folks
that need to know all of these muscles.
But again, I just put this slide up to
show you just
how muscular these horses are, how many
different muscles are working in
con, in conjunction with each other to
propel them, to allow them
to run, as fast as they do, and, and keep
them upright.
So, so pretty interesting to see all that.
Now, the digestive anatomy, we're going to
cover in greater depth during week four.
You know, what, what each organ does in
the digestive tract.
But again, just to kind of visualize, you
know, the, the viscera of the horse and
just how large these organs are if you've
ever seen them, you know, in a colic
surgery.
I've been fortunate enough to, to see a
couple of those,
and it's just amazing to see how large
these, these organs are.
And then going into week six, we'll, we'll
cover more into the reproductive anatomy.
Really focusing mainly a lot on the mare,
because that has a specific implications
for mare management.
Now, in our next lecture, we're going to
jump into hoof anatomy and so,
it's, it's just as important as some
of this external anatomy that we talked
about.
So, I look forward to seeing you then.