[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right.
Welcome back, and in this next lecture,
we're going to talk about coat markings.
So you know really again, the two areas
that we're going to
look at is, is the face, and then also the
leg.
So we're going to kind of walk through
this, and, and give
you the verbiage on what we call different
markings on the face.
So, you know, looking at this image, at
the end of this lecture,
you should easily be able to identify all
of these markings on these horses.
So, the first marking is what we call a
star.
And, these can be really subtle, really
light, I
mean, sometimes you just see some white
hair in there.
Or, they can be what I call bold,
they're really bright, you know, really,
really there.
So, you know, in this image, this would be
a faint
one and then this one would be like a
really bold star.
And if you wanted to see what this looked
like on, you know, actual horses.
So, here's one where it's just a very
faint star, this one's kind of middle
of the road, and not all the time,
you know, they're, they're going to be
different patterns.
They're, they're always not circular.
And then here's one with a pretty bold
star right there.
That, that's pretty out there, I mean,
you, you
can see that and you're like, Oh, that's a
star.
So, that's what we call, you know, any
marking, you know, between the eyes and
the forehead.
And then we'll go, we'll jump down to the,
to the
lips of the horse and then we call this a
snip.
So you can see here between the nasal
bones or
the upper lip of the horse, we call these
snips.
And again, they can be either really,
really
bold or they can be really, really subtle.
Again with these two, you know, obviously
here too.
You can see, really there's no more white
markings on that, that's just snips on the
horse.
And that's what we call that.
And then the middle one, is a strip, or
sometimes some people call a it stripe.
Which, either or is okay.
And the white is between the nasal bone.
So if you look at the nasal bone of the
horse
here and here, you can see the white in
between that.
So when, when we do see that then it's a
strip or a stripe.
Okay.
And again here, this horse is pretty bold,
but again, still
between the nasal bones we would still
call that a strip.
Now with most horses it's, you know,
they're going to
have a, a combination of these on the
face.
They're, they're either going to have one
or two or all three.
And we also call these, you know,
we either say they're continuous or
non-continuous.
So continuous is, you know, the best
example All three, or all four of these,
here, are continuous where, you know, you
have the star, the strip, and the snip.
So in all three of them, it's, they're all
running together.
Noncontinuous is, is the example right
here, where you do have
a star, you do have a strip, and you do
have a snip, but it's, it's broken.
So if you wanted to see this again on, on
real horses, here's one with a continuous
star strip snip.
Okay, and then on this foal you have a
star and a
strip, and then on this horse you have a
star and a snip.
Okay.
So, pretty easy with the facial markings.
Now, the one where people sometimes get
confused
and that's between a strip and a blaze.
Okay.
A blaze, we consider it a blaze anytime
that white
starts to either meet or exceed outside
those nasal bones.
So this picture is a pretty clear
definition of what we would call blaze.
Now again, seeing this on, on live horses,
this one here you
can definitely see that it's got the
flaxen mane, mane and tail.
You can see it's outside the nasal bones,
it's
clearly a blaze, and that's we call a
blaze.
Now this, it gets a little tricky, you
know,
once you get these horses that again are
in between.
Maybe somebody would say star, strip,
snip.
Okay.
I mean you can get away with that.
But again, you know, this you would
probably clearly define as a blaze because
it's
meet in the nasal bones or exceeding a
little bit of the nasal bones there.
So that's what a blaze would look like.
Now there's, there's some really cool
white
markings too that, that have some special
nomenclature.
And the first is a bald face so you can
see this full.
Where the white blaze extends past the
eyes, so you know, all of
the white is in the face, and we call that
a bald face.
And then the next one is really neat too,
and that's called an apron.
And this is where you get, you know, it,
it, again, it's called
an apron because it looks like somebody
put an apron over their face.
Where you get the white running up
almost underneath the throat latch with
this horse.
So that's what we call an apron.
And then one of my favorites.
I, I think this one's always great too, is
called the medicine hat.
And you can see it's just the dark areas
around the, the top of the head and the
ears.
So there, and if they have that, we call
that a medicine hat.
So I think it's, I think it's really cool,
I think it's really cool marking.
So the, that's kind of the, you know, sums
up most
of the facial markings that, that are most
common amongst horses.
The next is the leg markings, and we're
going to work our way up.
So we'll start at the hoof and work our
way up the leg And the first
one is when you just have some white just
along the hoof, or just above the hoof.
So we either call them a white heel
or, or you'll sometimes hear the term
ermine marks.
And in this next image, in these next two
images you can clearly see
where the white is along the heel here, so
that's pretty clearly a white heel.
And then, here you can see there's some
white here, white here.
And it's kind of non continuous.
Kindof spotty around there.
And those we would probably call ermine
marks.
So when there's just a little bit of white
above the hoof.
Now, if it is continuous runs all along
the hoof,
of the bottom of the hoof, around that
coronary band.
Remember, this is where that anatomy kind
of helps to, to remember
because a lot of these markings on the leg
refer to the anatomy.
And when there's just some white, just
above that, but really
not too far up the pasture, we would call
that a coronet.
Now, the next one is when you do have
white running up the
coronet, but does...or excuse me, from the
coronet up the pastern, but stops
at the fetlock here, so you can see it
runs all the way
up the pastern but stops at the fetlock,
and we'll call that a pastern.
Now this one you can see it's half way up
the pastern and some of the white runs up
here.
So you kind of see that so I'll make a
little boot.
So there you go.
So you can see where some of that white
runs up.
Some people may say that's a partial
pastern because it almost
looks like a cornet, but you have some
white running up it.
They would call that a partial pastern.
So, again looking on a live animal, or
what would be in a live animal,
rather than in a picture, there you can
see what is clearly marked a pastern.
Now, when it does go above the fetlock,
that's when we would call it a fetlock,
or sometimes you have that white running
up
partially, some people may call that a
partial fetlock.
So, here.
You can see here where it's about the
fetlock joint.
So here's the fetlock joint here, and it's
above it.
Almost a sock, which is our next one, but
not quite.
So we would probably call that a fetlock.
Now a sock, what we call a sock is
generally when
the white runs up about half-way up the
canon bone, okay.
But does not go up above the knee on the
front legs, or the hawk on the hind leg.
So this is the hock on the hind legs.
So the white is almost halfway up, but
doesn't
exceed there, so that's what we would call
a sock.
So again looking at these horses, you can
see the cannon
bone halfway, halfway, that's a sock,
halfway, halfway, those are socks.
Now again, if it ran up here, you can see
here again drawn that.
Weird looking boot there.
You can see where you know that would be
still a sock
so not quite the next one which is called
a, a stocking.
So a stocking is when it actually reaches
the hock or the knees or goes above it.
So here's what we call a stocking And then
here on,
on the left is clear two stockings on the
hind legs.
So that's what we would call a stocking.
Now this next one, we do have a stocking
here, okay.
So here's the knees, okay so that white is
meeting
the knees, but this one doesn't extend
past the knees.
Now there's a little bit of white here,
but not
quite, so this one we would probably still
call a sock.
And then, this one we would call a
stocking, okay?
Now the final thing we'll talk about with
identification is these
weird things called chestnuts, or some
people call them night eyes.
And again, this is what's so cool about
horses or equids you know,
donkeys have these to, is they, they think
this is a remnant from evolution.
Where, you know, if we remember, we went
from four, to three, to a single toed
animal.
And those, those toes migrated up the leg.
Well, they believe these, these chestnuts,
it's kind of just a, a remnant of that.
That that's still kind of around.
And what, what a lot of people believe,
too, is that these
really unique, each one's unique to
a horse where they're almost like
fingerprints.
Now, they do grow a little bit, so they
do, they,
they can scuff off kind of the dead skin
on there.
But some breed registries actually do
require photographs.
And like the jockey club in certain
circumstances will
actually require photography, you know
somebody have to go
in there and take a photograph of those
night
eyes as a, a unique mark to that animal.
So just be aware, you've always wondered
what
those weird things were, that's what they
are.
So that concludes the end of week two and
you know again this week we talked a
lot about hoof anatomy, you know
laminitis, hoof care
and then jumped into coat markings and
coat colors.
So just remind to take, take quiz two.
The quiz questions come directly from the
lectures and the slides so they
should be very, very straightforward if
you've been paying attention and taking
notes.
And also complete assignment one, so
that's going to be
due before week three which shouldn't take
you a whole heck
of a lot of time and you, I made a video
to clearly explain what the expectations
should be for that assignment.
And then you're going to be asked to do a
peer evaluation.
Of three, of at least three, of your peers
that
you can go in there and look at their
assignments.
Give them feedback, give them a score,
and that's going to be due by the end of
week
three, the beginning of week four.