All right, welcome back to the second
lecture
of week two, and this lecture is hoof
anatomy.
And, you know, we devote, you know, the
next three lectures
really just focusing on the hoof because
it is so critical
to their care that, you know, it's really
worth while to
pay attention to these lectures and
hopefully, give you some tips.
So, you know, it's really important to
maintain a horse's hoof.
And, you know, it's really critical to
their ability to move, you know?
So, if you're competing with this horse or
any type of activity, if
something's wrong with their feet, they're
not going to be able to go anywhere.
And it's just, it's really critical to
their, to their, you know, health and
well being, because, the old adage or the
old saying is no hoof, no horse.
And you know, I'm going to use Barbaro as
an example, and we're
going to get in much more detail when we
get in the laminitis talk.
You know, Barbaro is a story that happened
in 2006 in the United States.
He had won the Kentucky Derby.
Spectacular horse, people really thought
he was
the next great chance for a triple crown.
In the initial stretch of the Preakness
Stakes, he breaks his hind right leg.
And what happened was his hind right leg
healed fine.
It's just he started going laminitic in
all the rest of his feet.
And so, that, that's what really led to
his demise.
And he was euthanized in January of 2007.
So, you know that's what directly caused
him to, to no
longer be able to live, you know, he had
no feet.
Now, looking at anatomy, you know, we're
going to
start on the outside and work our way in.
And the first portion is just this outer
hoof portion,
and this is what we call insensitive, or
epidermal, tissue.
Now, it's insensitive because it doesn't
have the
nerve structure or really a lot of blood
flowing
in those areas, and I like to, to tell
students that it, it's almost like your
long fingernails.
You know, we clip our, our long
fingernails
all the time, and we don't feel anything.
You know, as long as it's the, the dead
portion
or out, outgrowth portion, which is very
similar to the horse.
So that's why we're able to put on, nail
shoes on,
or, or trim their feet, and they, they
feel no discomfort whatsoever.
Now, the bottom of the hoof anatomy is
really, really important to, to know
different structures.
So, it's worth while to review this slide
in detail.
You know, if you ever get in discussions
with a fairer or your
veterinarian, you need to know, you know,
what he or she is referencing to.
Now, just looking at the, the external
part, you know, divide the hoof into
really three parts, and the first portion
is called the toe.
So you can see here, the next portion is
the quarters.
And then there is this, this final portion
is what we call the heel.
So, we'll say heels, quarters, toe in
reference to that.
And just going around, this right here,
which I'll
highlight in later slides too, is called
the frog.
We'll talk about that.
You know, here's the bars of the frog in
here.
Most of this area, you know, is the sole.
So, you're looking at, you know, all the
way
through here is, is really the, the
concave portion of
the hoof, and then this outer portion, or
the hoof
wall, you know, is really going all the
way around.
And we'll talk about that too, especially
when we talk about hoof care,
but that's where the horse rests, or
should be resting, most of their weight.
They shouldn't be resting weight on the
sole or the frog,
that outer wall should really be the part
that's protruding down.
So, and we'll get to that when we talk
about hoof care.
Now, in this slide, I just put up the
bottom of a hoof
and just wanted to see if you could
identify some structures on your own.
So you can pause the video and try to go
back through that, and just compare it to
an actual hoof
on this slide and to the previous one,
with all the
different structures, and see if you can
find them on that.
Now one, one portion I did not talk about
in the previous slide is this
area that you can kind of see starting
right
here, and it goes all the way around.
And that's going to help lead us into,
you know, talking about the internal
structure.
But that's called the white line.
And the white line is where you get you
know,
the the inner hoof wall combining with the
outer hoof wall.
Now, the coronary band is this region
right here,
which you can see at the top of this hoof.
Okay.
And that's almost like our nail bed.
So, that's where the hoof grows out.
So, starting from there growing down is
where the hoof kind of originates.
So, if we look at our own nail beds, you
know, that's kind of very similar to the
coronary band.
Now, it's important to remember if, if
this gets injured or, you know,
sometimes horses can clip their, their
hooves
when, you know, exercising or what not.
You know, that can slow down or stop
growth.
So you always want to be careful if you do
have a horse that has
an injury there, to have a veterinarian
or, or a fairer look at that area.
Now, things that can affect hoof growth.
You know, you can see the list there.
And, and the two that I'll highlight is
nutrition.
And we know through research that, you
know,
hoof growth definitely has a, is affected
by nutrition.
And, and what we mean is, horses that have
a higher plane of nutrition or
they're, they have diets that are just
higher
in nutrients, they're going to have better
hoof growth.
And so, there are a bunch of
supplements in different markets
throughout the world that
sells hoof promotants, and, and you know,
some
of these have research; some of these
don't.
But the general knowledge or the general
rule
of thumb is better nutrients equal better
hoof growth.
And then the other one I'll highlight
really quickly too is the environment.
In dry areas of the world or when it's dry
times of the year, hoof growth is actually
going to slow down.
And then during more wet, you know, spring
season or
rainy season, those hooves are going to
grow a little bit faster.
Now, on average, a horse is going to grow,
the hoof's
going to grow about a quarter to have an
inch per month.
So, it takes anywhere from nine months to
a
year for a horse to fully grow out their
hooves.
Now, the other structure I really wanted
to address on the outer
hoof wall is this frog region, which you
can see it outlined there.
It's a little off center, but that, that's
on purpose so you can visualize that.
And the frog is the area of the hoof that
is, I guess if
you, if you said anywhere, an area was
sensitive, it would be the frog.
Now, there aren't, there isn't nerves
running through there.
But it's the softer portion of, of the
outer hoof.
So, it's made up of approximately 50%
moisture.
And, that's important because it really
helps
the hoof expand when they strike the
ground.
So it's almost the shock absorber.
And it gives that hoof a little bit of its
elasticity.
So, when the horse hits the ground, that
hoof actually kind of presses, compresses
and spreads out.
And that's why, you know, the frog with
that moisture content can kind of do that.
So, and when we get to talking about hoof
care, we'll address the frog a little bit
more,
you know, on, on being careful trimming
the frog,
because you, you can injure it if you
overdo it.
Now, going from the outside to the inside,
you know, the inside
we call the sensitive tissue or the dermal
layer, and you can
see you know, that looks like that's
pretty painful, you know, and
obviously that was a horse that, that was
euthanized at some point.
But you can see the, the rich blood supply
and that, when we
call it sensitive, that also means that
there's a lot of nerves there.
So again, like the bottom of our nailbed.
Anybody's that accidentally clipped their
nails too
short or pulled a nail, it's extremely
painful.
Well, that's because of all the nerves
that are in there
and very similar to a horse's hooves, you
know that internal tissue.
Now, I referenced the white line earlier,
and if you looked at, you know, going
from the external tissue to the internal
tissue, it would be this region right
here.
So, you're, you're, you're looking at the
portion where the outer hoof wall
is attaching to the inner hoof, and that's
through the laminar interface.
So, they have these interlocking fingers
that actually
are really tight, even down at the
microscopic level.
And they keep everything in place.
Now, also important with the, the, this
laminar
inter, interface is it attaches to the
coffin bone.
So, it keeps the coffin bone locked in at
the proper
angle, and it just really holds the
entire, the hoof structure together.
Now speaking of bones, these are three
bones that make up the hoof wall.
So we started with the short pastern or we
call it the P2 or second
phalanx, and then we have the navicular
bone
here, and then we have the coffin bone.
So these are the bones that make up the
hoof.
Now, this long pastern bone is actually P1
for the first phalanx.
And so that's really not part of the hoof,
but that's
coming down, you know, from the fetlock
down to the pastern.
Now, I'm only going to talk about two
tendons, and before I do that, understand
that
tendons is the portion of the connective
tissue that connects a muscle to a bone.
Whereas, ligaments attach bone to bone.
So, we talk about two really important
tendons that are important in the hoof.
And the first is the deep digital flexor
tendon or the DDFT.
And that attaches to the back of the
coffin bone, here.
So, we're looking right down here and
actually, it's, it's
up here where it attaches to the deep
digital flexor muscle.
Now, when that muscle contracts, so when
we contract the muscle, we actually
shorten it.
Okay.
So, you can imagine that's going to pull
this
tendon up, and this hoof is going to flex.
So it flexes back.
Okay.
So it pulls it back.
That's flexing.
And that's from the deep digital flexor
tendon.
Now, the other one is the common digital
extensor tendon.
And so if you imagine up here the common
digital extensor muscle actually
contracts, so it's shortens and pulls up
on this, and so
the hoof is going to extend so extends
out.
And that's how those two tendons work.
Now, there's other tendons running in
there, and
you know, the suspensory ligament and
other things that,
that are in part of the leg anatomy that
are important because horses do get
injuries there, but.
So just be aware that, that there are a
lot of, tendons and ligaments in there,
keeping all the structures together, but
these are
the two that I just wanted to highlight.
And then, the final slide kind of talking
about hoof
anatomy, and this will get important
especially when we run
into, start talking about laminitis is
there's a really rich
blood supply running down to the hoof, so
you can
see the, the the, you know, the many blood
vessels running through there, and it's
really critical, that helps
those tissues, you know, grow and sustain
themselves, and grow
the hoof, so, when we get to laminitis,
we'll know,
we'll talk about the importance of that a
little bit more in a couple lectures.
So next, we're going to jump into hoof
care.
So I'll see you then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]