All right, so
welcome to Week 2 of The Horse Course.
And here I am at the beautiful horse
teaching unit here in the University of
Florida's, kind of near campus,
we're about five minutes from main
campus in Gainesville, Florida.
And we're, we're sitting on about 40
acres that we use to teach a lot of our
students about horses, horse care,
and we actually have a riding arena
where students learn how to, you know,
ride and have fun with their horses.
So we're very,
very fortunate here in our animal sciences
department to have this facility.
And I'm lucky enough that we actually have
another facility about 30 miles south
in Ocala, Florida.
We have 355, or 3,
about 355 acre equine sciences center, and
that's where a lot of our mammas and
babies are right now.
So in some of our, our future lectures
you'll see some images from there and, and
videos from there.
So we are, are actually very, very lucky
here at Florida to have a wonderful equine
department, equine faculty and
animal science department you know,
and able to, to give you this
information through Coursera.
Now, going into Week 2 we're going to
cover some basic physiology,
we're going to get into hoof care,
you know, hoof physiology, laminitis,
really the importance of why, you know, we
need to take care of those horse's feet.
And then we're going to round out the wee,
the week talking about coat colors and
coat markings.
Now, don't forget to take the quizzes.
You still have time to take Quiz 1 and
Quiz 2, so
those deadlines are a little bit longer.
And then this week we actually
are starting the, the own a horse project.
And we have to have strict deadlines
with that because we are doing peer
evaluations.
And so we need to,
you to get your work submitted so
next week you can go in and evaluate three
of your peers and give them feedback.
So look into that, watch the video that we
posted on there describing the project,
and go ahead and submit that.
So the first week has been phenomenal.
Again, you know, this is the second
iteration of the horse course.
In the first iteration we had
close to 15,000 students,
learners from around the world.
This time we still have over 5,000
from over 130 different countries.
So there's over 5,000 of you out there,
and it's just, it's, it's, it's awesome.
It's amazing to me
the reach of this course.
You know, a couple shout outs
to Baoyi from inner Mongolia.
I know I posted and said, you know,
welcome to the course in his thread.
I was really excited to
see somebody from there.
And then again,
Lily from Tampa a young lady who,
who came after last summer, after watching
the horse course the first time, came and
visited with me with her family.
And she, I saw she was enrolled again.
And then Genesis one of my
ex-students who graduated from here
is also taking the course,
so shout out to them.
And then just quickly, you know, there
were some really really cool threads week.
Julia had a thread, she's from Delaware.
You know, asking what's the purpose
of a zorse or a zonkey, and you know,
without, you know,
jumping into the thread there, I thought
I would address it through the video.
I think it's more of a novelty thing.
I think that's why people, you know,
breed these animals, to kind of see.
Unlike when you had a mule, you know, that
animal was bred for a specific purpose,
you know, crossing the horse and donkeys.
Whereas the zorse and
zonkeys are more just kind of
a novelty thing in my opinion.
And then Vasiliki, if I, if I'm saying
that right, from Greece you know,
asked about American Indians,
you know Native Americans and horses.
And in my lectures, you know, I talk about
how horses originated in North America,
and then went extinct about 10.000
years ago from this part of the world.
And they weren't reintroduced until the
Spanish came and the conquistadors, and
some of their animals got away from them,
or the Native Americans, you know,
got their hands on them.
And then those horses and, and
the wild American horses that
you see became established.
So it wasn't until then did you see
horses back in this part of the world.
And then Nazaret from, the Canary Islands
started a post on local breeds,
from around the world and
people are posting images.
So I, I, I highly suggest you, go to that
thread, look at some of the pictures,
it's, It's, It's really great.
And the interactions between the students,
between you all in the first week has just
been phenomenal and let's keep it up for
the next few weeks.
So I'll check in next week,
beginning of Week 3.
Have a great week.
See me on the, the message boards.
If you have any questions,
please, you know,
feel free to join in and, and
get in there and ask your questions and,
and other students or myself will
go in there and try to answer them.
So, I look forward to
seeing you next week.