Alright, welcome back.
And in this lecture,
we're going to talk about hoof care.
And again, this is one that, that I
decided to re-record from the first run.
Really, when I initially did this, I,I,
I didn't intend to teach people
how to trim a, a horses foot.
I, I just wanted to review it because
it's such a critical part of their,
their health.
So, I'm just going to put
this disclaimer upfront that,
that's not the intention of this lecture.
It's not to teach you how to
properly trim a horses foot because
really that should be done by
a trained professional or you,
yourself can go out and get trained
on how to do this with your animal.
But if you do this improperly, you can
injure them, so we, we don't want that,
that's not the intention of this.
It's just to give you the information
on maybe what a farrier or
a trained professional is looking at,
when they're trimming their feet.
So, just keep that in mind as
we go through this lecture.
Now, it's always good to review
the anatomy because, you know,
in the previous lectures, we were
talking about the importance of that.
So here, you can see the,
the anatomy of the bottom of the hoof,
and we're going to kind of
talk about some of this.
Now, why do we need to trim a,
a horses hoof?
What, you know, what's going on?
And really, you know,
we took these animals from the wild
where they would be out, you know
naturally wearing down their hooves.
Their hooves would be adjusting to
the environment that they're in and
they would get natural wear and tear.
But as soon as we put them in pastures,
or stalls or paddocks.
We've taken away that opportunity for
them to, to wear down their hooves.
So, you know, we, that's why we
have to take care of their feet.
Now this image on the right.
You can see, that, that is a,
a severely neglected, neglected animal.
I, I only put this in here to show you,
you know, how the hoof grows.
And what happens if we
don't take care of them.
So a little shock value.
I apologize.
But, again, that's why it's so important.
And we really,
really need to take care of these animals.
Now, in nature, if, you know,
let's say zebra, you know, being chased
here by a lion, has hoof problems well,
they're going to get picked off.
And, you know, if, if, if you look at, you
know, how nature works, if an animal has
an injury or an illness, you know, they're
going to get picked off by a predator.
Those genetics generally won't be passed
on, you know to the, to the future,
so horses that are in the wild or
are wild equids tend to have strong feet.
You know, they, they've kind of
evolved that way, whereas you know,
in domestication we really haven't
selected these animals too much,
especially in, you know,
recent years to have strong feet.
That we really have selected them for
performance or
how they look, stuff like that.
Now, you know, again, it's a,
you know, just to reiterate why we
need to take care of those feet.
If not, it, it can develop, you know, foot
diseases, things that we call, you know,
lameness or laminitis, which you're
going to get in the next lecture.
So again,
that's why we want to take care of them.
Now this is something everybody should do,
you know, whether you, you,
know how to trim a hoof or
not, or you're a farrier or
not, everybody should inspect
their animals' feet daily.
You know, especially when we get to
the health lectures we'll talk about,
you know, inspecting your animal daily to
make sure they're, they're healthy and
everything's okay and
they don't have any, you know, wounds.
This is something you want to do,
you want to pick up their feet daily and
clean their feet daily, which in the next
slide we talk about, with a hoof pick.
So most you know anybody and
if you need you know,
someone to show you how to do this,
it's relatively simple.
To get a hoof pick, you know,
you, you probably to do need to know how
to you know, properly restrain a horse.
And then also how to pick
their feet up safely.
So you, you definitely want somebody to,
to show you how to do that.
But once you do and you know how to hold
their feet, you know, when you're picking
their feet, you always want to start
at the heel and work towards the toe.
And the reason we do
that is you don't want
this hoof pick driving into
the soft tissue of the frog.
Which you've gotten in
the previous lectures.
You know,
the frog has high moisture content,
so you actually can injure them or
injure the frog.
So you always want to start at the heel,
and work towards the toe, and
you just want to clean that debris out,
to, to keep the hoof healthy.
Now, getting into, to hoof trimming,
again, that disclaimer that you
really only want to do this if
you're a trained professional.
But you want your horse to get their feet
trimmed about every six to eight weeks.
If you, if you remember the,
the previous lecture, you know the,
the hoofs grow at about
half an inch a month.
So it grows relatively quickly.
Kind of like our fingernails or toenails.
So you want someone to come out and
take care of their feet.
Now, that's going to vary, obviously,
on all those things we talked about,
environment, and
how they're being used but, you know,
you definitely want them to,
to come out and look.
Now, I put this image in here.
This is, again, a neglected animal but
just to show you that the toe
does grow faster than the heal.
I mean, that's a really,
really overgrown toe.
On that poor animal.
But just to get that kind of image
burned in your mind that the toe does
grow faster with that.
And then also another note
again with that frog,
we want to be really careful around the
frog because it's that softer tissue, so.
If you cut too much of the frog, or
you know, trim too much of the frog,
it can injure them and
lead to further problems.
So anytime you're working with the frog,
you just want to,
you just want to be careful.
[COUGH] Now, when a professional
is looking at your, your animal,
what they're going to be looking at is,
is hoof balance.
Okay.
And we're going to show you
different angles of this and, and how they
may be looking at that animal's hoof.
So, you know, they want to make sure that
hoof is, is carrying that animal and
is distributing the weight evenly, okay?
If not, then that can actually lead to,
to, not only, you know, foot lameness, but
other issues, too, with muscles and,
and joints and stuff like that.
So, you want to make sure,
you know, their health really,
kind of starts, begin, begins at the feet.
And we want to make sure that,
it's properly balanced.
Okay, and so
to continue this hoof balance, you know,
I found this from this wonderful website,
talking about, you know, heel toe issues.
You know, with confirmation.
So just to show you, you know, this image
on the left says it has a heel issue.
So what that means is, we've really
gotta kind of trim some of the heel,
that would carry this foot
a little bit forward.
Now this second image, right here.
Has a toe issue.
So you, to bring that back in line you'd
want to probably trim some of the toe and
that would bring it back there.
Because really what we want is them
standing square on top of that hoof.
So again, it would take a,
a trained professional looking
at your animal to see that.
Now.
Also when they're trimming their feet
they want to look at it from the side.
So you can see here, you know,
with these three images.
You know the, the first one on
the left is called Broken-Back so
we always look,
like to look at the pastern.
The angle of the pastern in the hoof.
So here's Ideal,
it's almost a straight line.
And then here you can see
the angle of the pastern.
That's called Broken-Forward.
So what we need to do is trim
either some of the toe or
the heel to bring that back in line.
Now, starting with the front one we would
want to trim off some of that toe and
that would actually rotate
this back a little bit.
To bring it into the ideal position.
In the broken forward we would trim
off a little bit of the heal and
that would drop the foot to bring
it in line with the paster angle.
But again, a trained professional,
that's what they're looking for and
that's probably what
they're doing with it.
Now in this image you can see,
you know, a hoof that is improper.
Or this is a neglected animal.
And then this is the proper, you know,
shape of the hoof that we're looking for.
So I think this image kind of shows you,
you know, what we're trying to get.
Now if you came across an animal that was
this overgrown you would not want to trim
it to this, again you want a farrier
professional to do this because you know,
especially, an animal that
has an overgrown hoof,
if you just all the sudden get it
back into what it should look like,
perfect, you know, it could cause issues
and some soreness and stuff like that.
So again, a trained professional
is somebody that can do that.
Now, just to give you a couple examples,
again I wanted to show you this one.
So if you look at the pastern angle.
And then the hoof angle.
So if you ask yourself would I need to,
to remove some of the toe or
would I need to remove some of
the heel to bring that back in line.
So let's say we remove some of the heel,
what would that do?
Okay so if we,
if we, if we you know trimmed it down
here what that would do is drop the hoof.
And would bring this angle up.
So that's not what we want to do.
What we'd actually want to do with
this one is trim some of the toe.
Okay, and
that will drop the hoof a little bit.
And that will get it more in length,
in angle with the pastern, okay?
Now with this one,
I also included a couple images.
So here's your file.
Which generally is like a nail-file.
So, it's, it's generally safer to use,
especially if you're learning
how to do this in the beginning.
You do have to be careful first,
it will cut you.
They, they are sharp.
I've, I've cut my hands on them
by grabbing them wrong before.
And also, you can take a lot
of hoof off rather quickly.
So, you know,
you want to use the finer side and
work slowly especially when you're if,
if you're a novice and
you're trying to learn how to do this,
you know, under trained, eyes.
The next is the nippers which again you
have to be extremely cautious using.
This can take off a lot of hoof fast.
So again, you don't want to use this,
unless you're really tra, trained.
And then this hoof knife.
And actually have for, for righties and
lefties they, they make different hoof
knives and that's actually to help with
the sole and, and some other things.
So if you look at this,
this image of this hoof here, obviously,
we've got some overgrown parts.
The frogs pretty overgrown
a little bit here.
And you can see the, the, just the overall
shape of, of the hoof isn't too bad.
But that hoof definitely has some
areas where it needs to be trimmed.
And this is probably something, you know,
if you waited eight weeks you would see
and say okay I need to look at that.
Here's some areas that are sticking out,
I need to trim here and there.
But again, it, it, it could be a whole
Coursera course on hoof trimming
just to get you almost ready to be able
to pick up a hoof and, and start to,
to trim it properly.
So there's that.
Now the last part of this is shoeing.
And, you know,
we had some interesting discussions when,
when I've talked about this in,
in the previous version of Coursera.
And different attitudes.
And, and I've looked at some research.
And some, there's some
interesting research coming out,
I think it was out of Michigan State,
talking about how hooves,
you know, are stronger if, if they're
barefoot and left alone over time.
So there is some research starting to
emerge that leaving horses barefoot can,
can actually be better for them.
But again, since we use these animals in,
in all different types of situations.
That doesn't necessarily mean we,
we would never want to shoe them.
And shoeing is, is, is really often
necessary to protect the animal.
So, you know,
what are some of the things that,
that shoeing does is it helps reduces
wear on the, on the, on the feet.
And, you know, from my own
experience on a research project,
I had some mares exercising.
In kind of a, sandy, you know,
free, free flow exerciser, and
their hooves were really
getting worn down.
And we had to put shoes on them,
to protect their feet.
Because I,
I didn't want to harm them obviously.
So, you know,
that was one area where, you know,
if you noticed the use of the animal, and
they're really starting to get, you know.
Thin hooves and, and low,
you definitely want to put shoes on them.
Now, for some of these animals that
are actually ridden on asphalt or
concrete you know for
their work you know like police
horses often times they're going to need
shoes which is going to help traction,
there's also rubber shoes that help
cushion these animals a little bit.
And then obviously any time a, a trained
professional or a farrier says hey,
we need some corrective shoeing to,
to help your animal or
a veterinarian recommends that, obviously
you're going to need to put shoes on them.
So, so sometimes we,
we do need it, need it.
And, it's really just up to
your individual situation.
So, you know, again,
based on your chosen activity.
And, and I would say if your animal's kept
in pasture and that's, that's their life,
they're not being ridden
really all that much, or
they're not out on hard surfaces,
stuff like that, will you need shoes?
Probably not.
I mean,
you're not going to need them out there.
But you still need to
check your animal's feet.
They still need to be cleaned daily.
And they still need their hooves trimmed,
so don't forget that.
Just because they're not on pasture,
doesn't mean you forget about them,
you, you have to really take care of them.
Now if you're out competing, out riding a
lot, yeah, most likely yes, because again
like I said in my own personal experience,
you know these animals, constant wear on
their feet, going over hard surfaces,
they're getting that wear and tear.
So shoes will help protect them.
But, best advice like always is talk to
a professional, talk to your farrier.
Have them look at your animal.
Talk to him about what you're doing.
And they'll give you the best advice then.
Alright, so that's it.
So what's next?
Next is, you know, obviously not a very
fun topic but very, very important.
And that's laminitis.
So I'll see you then.
[MUSIC]
Oops.