All right.
In this video, we are just going to do a,
a quick
tutorial on the weekly assignment and
kind of what the expectations are.
I, I really felt like this would help you
kind of understand what's
expected, and the whole idea of this, you
know, weekly assignment that
we're doing in the horse course, is for
you to take the
information that we're, we're giving each
week, and apply it to an animal.
You know, as an educator I always feel,
when, when students apply the information.
They tend to retain it more, you know, and
longer.
So, for this assignment, in the beginning
we're asking you to choose an
animal, a, you know any type of equid that
you would like to own.
Whether it's a horse, donkey, mule, or a
hy.
Other type of hybrid, or a zebra, you
know,
use your imagination if you're choosing a
hypothetical animal.
If you actually own horses, donkeys, mules
etc.
You can actually choose one of them and
apply the assignments each week to that
animal.
Now, you know, for a quick brief
description, you know, in my example I
would say I, I'm choosing a horse i'm
going to choose an American quarter horse.
And it's going to be a gelding.
And then I'm actually going to use this
animal, to do western pleasure riding.
And that's all we would, we, you know, I'm
asking you to use in your description.
That way when each week, you know, and
that's going to affect the
type of assignments you know, or the type
of plans that you develop.
You know, for example, I'm, I'm doing
western pleasure riding.
That means I need to ride this animal
almost every day, you know,
through the, throughout the week, doing
training,
so that's going to affect its nutrition
status.
That's going to affect my health care
plan.
That has many implications, so.
So, you know, choose what you'd like and
just write a brief description on that.
And then the real focus of this week's
assignment is a hoof care plan.
And, we've gone through all the, the
information, you know, from basic
hoof care going all the way to laminitis
and why it's so important.
So, so the first, you know, part of that
hoof care plan is.
You know, trimming feet.
And you have to ask yourself, you know,
how often am I going to do this?
So you go back in the notes and look at
frequency, look at the place where you
live in the world.
You know, look at those different factors.
And kind of get an idea, well, for this
animal
I probably have to do it every six weeks.
Or, you know, for this animal, you know,
it's pretty dry, arid region, maybe every
eight weeks.
So, you know, decide on that.
And then ask yourself, am I going to do
this myself, or am
I going to have a farrier come in and do
it for me?
So, if you're doing it yourself, then I'm
going to ask
you to look up your supplies, a hoof pick
and all
the other stuff you may, you may need, and
just come
up with a brief list, not a very co,
comprehensive list.
But just a brief list of the tools you'll
need,
and, and, and price those out using your
local currency.
Where you are in the world.
Now if you are using a farrier.
Then, then find out how much it would cost
for
a farrier to come in and trim all four
feet.
So you could make a quick phone call.
You can look on the internet.
Use any resource you want.
You know, even in the local paper.
And get an idea of how much a hoof trim
would cost you.
All right, and then this is the second
question on
this assignment is, are you going to put
shoes on your animal?
So, you know if, if, if you're not
going to shoe your
animal, then just briefly in, in a couple
of sentences state why.
You know, I want to keep my animal
barefoot because, or I really, you
know, I'm going to keep them on pasture
and not ride them very much, etc.
So, so that's how you would, you would
reason that.
If you do plan on shoeing your animal,
then just find out from your
farrier how much it's going to cost to put
four shoes on all four hooves,
so a one time deal, you know, how much it
would cost you in
your local currency, and then that's it,
so that's it for this week's assignment.
Now, for evaluation, you're actually
going to evaluate your peers.
So we're going to ask you to go in each
week, and evaluate at least three of your
peers.
You're just checking for completeness, and
that it's pretty accurate.
Now, remember, a lot of folks in this
class, enrolled in this class.
English may not be their primary language.
So we're not grading on grammar and
spelling.
But we're really looking at content.
So, you know, are they going to trim their
feet often enough?
Do the prices look reasonable?
And, and again, if it's in local
currency, that's going to be hard to
kind of evaluate.
and, so you're going to complete this
assignment by
the end of this week, of week two.
And, then you're peer evals will be due by
the end of week three.
So they're a week behind.
We'll release those at the beginning of
week three, and then
you finish 'em and finish 'em by the end
of week three.
And then we'll move on to the next
assignment.
[BLANK_AUDIO]